Hey, hi.
I'm Tim Gipson.
I'm going to talk to you about how you use a hand plane.
Now a hand plane is a very useful tool when you actually want to smooth out or take a curve out of the edge of the board.
Typically you'll do this when you want to take two boards, such as this, and you want to glue them up to make a larger panel.
Now the important thing when you get ready to use a hand plane is, on the blade, you want to make sure you always start with a sharp blade.
So, if...it's recommended before you start using your plane that you take your blade and you hone it.
And you can hone it on any kind of a sharpening block with a little bit of oil, which, this one's ready to go.
Now, the next thing you want to do, is, you want to check the setting of your blade.
And the best way to do this is to actually look down your plane, and there are two adjustment knobs.
There's a depth adjustment knob, which is here, and then there's also an angle lever here.
The angle will actually....it controls the tilt of the blade to make sure that you're getting a nice, even cut.
And we want to actually adjust this so that when we plane our board, we actually get a paper thin shaving of wood off our...our piece.
Now when we're starting to plane, we want to firmly hold the handle and the knob, and when we start our stroke, we want to make sure that the pressure is on the toe.
This keeps you from taking too big of a cut on your entrance.
And then when you finish your cut, you're going to finish with your pressure on your heel.
And again, that allows you to take a nice, even cut.
And you want to make nice, long, even strokes when you do this.
Okay?
So with a nice, long, even stroke you should be able to take and plane off a full section, just like that.
And the other thing to keep in mind is make sure that when you're...the piece that you're planing, that it's clamped in some kind of vice.
In this case I've got a table vice that I'm using and I've actually got the piece where it's elevated just a little bit.
And that'll help you in making sure that you make good cuts with your plane.
So I'm Tim Gipson, and that's how to use a hand plane.